Now, I'm an ethnobotanist. That's a scientist who works in the rainforest to document how people use local plants. I've been doing this for a long time, and I want to tell you, these people know these forests and these medicinal treasures better than we do and better than we ever will. But also, these cultures, these indigenous cultures, are disappearing much faster than the forests themselves. And the greatest and most endangered species in the Amazon Rainforest is not the jaguar, it's not the harpy eagle, it's the isolated and uncontacted tribes. Now four years ago, I injured my foot in a climbing accident and I went to the doctor. She gave me heat, she gave me cold, aspirin, narcotic painkillers, anti-inflammatories, cortisone shots. It didn't work. Several months later, I was in the northeast Amazon, walked into a village, and the shaman said, "You're limping." And I'll never forget this as long as I live. He looked me in the face and he said, "Take off your shoe and give me your machete." (Laughter) He walked over to a palm tree and carved off a fern, threw it in the fire, applied it to my foot, threw it in a pot of water, and had me drink the tea. The pain disappeared for seven months. When it came back, I went to see the shaman again. He gave me the same treatment, and I've been cured for three years now. Who would you rather be treated by? (Applause) Now, make no mistake — Western medicine is the most successful system of healing ever devised, but there's plenty of holes in it. Where's the cure for breast cancer? Where's the cure for schizophrenia? Where's the cure for acid reflux? Where's the cure for insomnia? The fact is that these people can sometimes, sometimes, sometimes cure things we cannot. Here you see a medicine man in the northeast Amazon treating leishmaniasis, a really nasty protozoal disease that afflicts 12 million people around the world. Western treatment are injections of antimony. They're painful, they're expensive, and they're probably not good for your heart; it's a heavy metal. This man cures it with three plants from the Amazon Rainforest. This is the magic frog. My colleague, the late great Loren McIntyre, discoverer of the source lake of the Amazon, Laguna McIntyre in the Peruvian Andes, was lost on the Peru-Brazil border about 30 years ago. He was rescued by a group of isolated Indians called the Matsés. They beckoned for him to follow them into the forest, which he did. There, they took out palm leaf baskets. There, they took out these green monkey frogs — these are big suckers, they're like this — and they began licking them. It turns out, they're highly hallucinogenic. McIntyre wrote about this and it was read by the editor of High Times magazine. You see that ethnobotanists have friends in all sorts of strange cultures. This guy decided he would go down to the Amazon and give it a whirl, or give it a lick, and he did, and he wrote, "My blood pressure went through the roof, I lost full control of my bodily functions, I passed out in a heap, I woke up in a hammock six hours later, felt like God for two days." (Laughter) An Italian chemist read this and said, "I'm not really interested in the theological aspects of the green monkey frog. What's this about the change in blood pressure?" Now, this is an Italian chemist who's working on a new treatment for high blood pressure based on peptides in the skin of the green monkey frog, and other scientists are looking at a cure for drug-resistant Staph aureus. How ironic if these isolated Indians and their magic frog prove to be one of the cures. Here's an ayahuasca shaman in the northwest Amazon, in the middle of a yage ceremony. I took him to Los Angeles to meet a foundation officer looking for support for monies to protect their culture. This fellow looked at the medicine man, and he said, "You didn't go to medical school, did you?" The shaman said, "No, I did not." He said, "Well, then what can you know about healing?" The shaman looked at him and he said, "You know what? If you have an infection, go to a doctor. But many human afflictions are diseases of the heart, the mind and the spirit. Western medicine can't touch those. I cure them." (Applause) But all is not rosy in learning from nature about new medicines. This is a viper from Brazil, the venom of which was studied at the Universidade de São Paulo here. It was later developed into ACE inhibitors. This is a frontline treatment for hypertension. Hypertension causes over 10 percent of all deaths on the planet every day. This is a $4 billion industry based on venom from a Brazilian snake, and the Brazilians did not get a nickel. This is not an acceptable way of doing business. The rainforest has been called the greatest expression of life on Earth. There's a saying in Suriname that I dearly love: "The rainforests hold answers to questions we have yet to ask." But as you all know, it's rapidly disappearing. Here in Brazil, in the Amazon, around the world. I took this picture from a small plane flying over the eastern border of the Xingu indigenous reserve in the state of Mato Grosso to the northwest of here. The top half of the picture, you see where the Indians live. The line through the middle is the eastern border of the reserve. Top half Indians, bottom half white guys. Top half wonder drugs, bottom half just a bunch of skinny-ass cows. Top half carbon sequestered in the forest where it belongs, bottom half carbon in the atmosphere where it's driving climate change. In fact, the number two cause of carbon being released into the atmosphere is forest destruction. But in talking about destruction, it's important to keep in mind that the Amazon is the mightiest landscape of all. It's a place of beauty and wonder. The biggest anteater in the world lives in the rain forest, tips the scale at 90 pounds. The goliath bird-eating spider is the world's largest spider. It's found in the Amazon as well. The harpy eagle wingspan is over seven feet. And the black cayman — these monsters can tip the scale at over half a ton. They're known to be man-eaters. The anaconda, the largest snake, the capybara, the largest rodent. A specimen from here in Brazil tipped the scale at 201 pounds. Let's visit where these creatures live, the northeast Amazon, home to the Akuriyo tribe. Uncontacted peoples hold a mystical and iconic role in our imagination. These are the people who know nature best. These are the people who truly live in total harmony with nature. By our standards, some would dismiss these people as primitive. "They don't know how to make fire, or they didn't when they were first contacted." But they know the forest far better than we do. The Akuriyos have 35 words for honey, and other Indians look up to them as being the true masters of the emerald realm. Here you see the face of my friend Pohnay. When I was a teenager rocking out to the Rolling Stones in my hometown of New Orleans, Pohnay was a forest nomad roaming the jungles of the northeast Amazon in a small band, looking for game, looking for medicinal plants, looking for a wife, in other small nomadic bands. But it's people like these that know things that we don't, and they have lots of lessons to teach us. However, if you go into most of the forests of the Amazon, there are no indigenous peoples. This is what you find: rock carvings which indigenous peoples, uncontacted peoples, used to sharpen the edge of the stone axe. These cultures that once danced, made love, sang to the gods, worshipped the forest, all that's left is an imprint in stone, as you see here. Let's move to the western Amazon, which is really the epicenter of isolated peoples. Each of these dots represents a small, uncontacted tribe, and the big reveal today is we believe there are 14 or 15 isolated groups in the Colombian Amazon alone. Why are these people isolated? They know we exist, they know there's an outside world. This is a form of resistance. They have chosen to remain isolated, and I think it is their human right to remain so. Why are these the tribes that hide from man? Here's why. Obviously, some of this was set off in 1492. But at the turn of the last century was the rubber trade. The demand for natural rubber, which came from the Amazon, set off the botanical equivalent of a gold rush. Rubber for bicycle tires, rubber for automobile tires, rubber for zeppelins. It was a mad race to get that rubber, and the man on the left, Julio Arana, is one of the true thugs of the story. His people, his company, and other companies like them killed, massacred, tortured, butchered Indians like the Witotos you see on the right hand side of the slide. Even today, when people come out of the forest, the story seldom has a happy ending. These are Nukaks. They were contacted in the '80s. Within a year, everybody over 40 was dead. And remember, these are preliterate societies. The elders are the libraries. Every time a shaman dies, it's as if a library has burned down. They have been forced off their lands. The drug traffickers have taken over the Nukak lands, and the Nukaks live as beggars in public parks in eastern Colombia. From the Nukak lands, I want to take you to the southwest, to the most spectacular landscape in the world: Chiribiquete National Park. It was surrounded by three isolated tribes and thanks to the Colombian government and Colombian colleagues, it has now expanded. It's bigger than the state of Maryland. It is a treasure trove of botanical diversity. It was first explored botanically in 1943 by my mentor, Richard Schultes, seen here atop the Bell Mountain, the sacred mountains of the Karijonas. And let me show you what it looks like today. Flying over Chiribiquete, realize that these lost world mountains are still lost. No scientist has been atop them. In fact, nobody has been atop the Bell Mountain since Schultes in '43. And we'll end up here with the Bell Mountain just to the east of the picture. Let me show you what it looks like today. Not only is this a treasure trove of botanical diversity, not only is it home to three isolated tribes, but it's the greatest treasure trove of pre-Colombian art in the world: over 200,000 paintings. The Dutch scientist Thomas van der Hammen described this as the Sistine Chapel of the Amazon Rainforest. But move from Chiribiquete down to the southeast, again in the Colombian Amazon. Remember, the Colombian Amazon is bigger than New England. The Amazon's a big forest, and Brazil's got a big part of it, but not all of it. Moving down to these two national parks, Cahuinari and Puré in the Colombian Amazon — that's the Brazilian border to the right — it's home to several groups of isolated and uncontacted peoples. To the trained eye, you can look at the roofs of these malocas, these longhouses, and see that there's cultural diversity. These are, in fact, different tribes. As isolated as these areas are, let me show you how the outside world is crowding in. Here we see trade and transport increased in Putumayo. With the diminishment of the Civil War in Colombia, the outside world is showing up. To the north, we have illegal gold mining, also from the east, from Brazil. There's increased hunting and fishing for commercial purposes. We see illegal logging coming from the south, and drug runners are trying to move through the park and get into Brazil. This, in the past, is why you didn't mess with isolated Indians. And if it looks like this picture is out of focus because it was taken in a hurry, here's why. (Laughter) This looks like — (Applause) This looks like a hangar from the Brazilian Amazon. This is an art exhibit in Havana, Cuba. A group called Los Carpinteros. This is their perception of why you shouldn't mess with uncontacted Indians. But the world is changing. These are Mashco-Piros on the Brazil-Peru border who stumbled out of the jungle because they were essentially chased out by drug runners and timber people. And in Peru, there's a very nasty business. It's called human safaris. They will take you in to isolated groups to take their picture. Of course, when you give them clothes, when you give them tools, you also give them diseases. We call these "inhuman safaris." These are Indians again on the Peru border, who were overflown by flights sponsored by missionaries. They want to get in there and turn them into Christians. We know how that turns out. What's to be done? Introduce technology to the contacted tribes, not the uncontacted tribes, in a culturally sensitive way. This is the perfect marriage of ancient shamanic wisdom and 21st century technology. We've done this now with over 30 tribes, mapped, managed and increased protection of over 70 million acres of ancestral rainforest. (Applause) So this allows the Indians to take control of their environmental and cultural destiny. They also then set up guard houses to keep outsiders out. These are Indians, trained as indigenous park rangers, patrolling the borders and keeping the outside world at bay. This is a picture of actual contact. These are Chitonahua Indians on the Brazil-Peru border. They've come out of the jungle asking for help. They were shot at, their malocas, their longhouses, were burned. Some of them were massacred. Using automatic weapons to slaughter uncontacted peoples is the single most despicable and disgusting human rights abuse on our planet today, and it has to stop. (Applause) But let me conclude by saying, this work can be spiritually rewarding, but it's difficult and it can be dangerous. Two colleagues of mine passed away recently in the crash of a small plane. They were serving the forest to protect those uncontacted tribes. So the question is, in conclusion, is what the future holds. These are the Uray people in Brazil. What does the future hold for them, and what does the future hold for us? Let's think differently. Let's make a better world. If the climate's going to change, let's have a climate that changes for the better rather than the worse. Let's live on a planet full of luxuriant vegetation, in which isolated peoples can remain in isolation, can maintain that mystery and that knowledge if they so choose. Let's live in a world where the shamans live in these forests and heal themselves and us with their mystical plants and their sacred frogs. Thanks again. (Applause)
Soy etnobotánico; un científico que trabaja en la selva documentando el uso que la gente le da a las plantas autóctonas. Hago esto desde hace mucho tiempo y quiero decirles que esta gente conoce los bosques y estos tesoros medicinales mejor que Uds. o yo. Pero además, estas culturas, las culturas indígenas, están desapareciendo mucho más rápido que los propios bosques. La principal especie en peligro de extinción en la selva Amazónica no es el jaguar, no es el águila arpía, sino los tribus aisladas y remotas. Hace ahora 4 años, me lesioné el pie en un accidente de escalada y fui al médico. Me recetó compresas calientes, compresas frías, aspirinas, analgésicos, anti-inflamatorios, inyecciones de cortisona. No funcionó. Varios meses después, estaba en el noreste del Amazonas, entré en una aldea, el chamán me dijo: "Estás cojeando", y nunca olvidaré esto mientras viva. Me miró a la cara y me dijo: "Quítate el zapato y dame el machete". (Risas) Se acercó a una palmera, cortó un helecho, lo tiró en el fuego, me lo aplicó en el pie, lo tiró en una olla con agua, y me hizo beber el té. El dolor desapareció durante 7 meses. Cuando volvió a dolerme, me fui a ver al chamán de nuevo. Me hizo lo mismo, y llevo 3 años curado. ¿Por quién prefieren ser atendidos? (Aplausos) Ahora, no nos engañemos, la medicina occidental es el sistema sanitario de más éxito en la historia, pero tiene muchas deficiencias. ¿Dónde está la cura para el cáncer de mama? ¿Para la esquizofrenia? ¿Dónde está la cura para el reflujo gastroesofágico? ¿Dónde está la cura para el insomnio? El hecho es que esta gente a veces puede, a veces, a veces, sanar cosas que nosotros no podemos. Aquí vemos a un curandero del noreste del Amazonas tratando la leishmaniosis, una enfermedad parasitaria realmente desagradable que aflige a 12 millones de personas en todo el mundo. El tratamiento en occidente consiste en inyecciones de antimonio. Duele, es caro, y probablemente no es bueno para el corazón; es un metal pesado. Este hombre lo cura con 3 plantas de la selva amazónica. Esta es la rana mágica. Mi gran colega, Loren McIntyre, ya fallecido, descubrió la fuente del Amazonas la laguna McIntyre en los Andes peruanos, se perdió en la frontera entre Perú y Brasil, hace 30 años. Fue rescatado por un grupo de indígenas aislados llamados matsés. Le dejaron señas para que las siguiera en el bosque, lo cual hizo. Luego, sacaron unas cestas de hojas de palma. Y, de ellas, sacaron estas ranas mono verdes --son grandes los bichos, así de grandes-- y empezaron a lamerlas. Resulta que son extremadamente alucinógenas. McIntyre escribió sobre eso y el editor de la revista High Times leyó sus palabras; ya ven que los etnobotánicos tienen amigos en todo tipo de culturas extrañas. (Risas) Y el hombre decidió irse al Amazonas y probarlo; lo hizo y después escribió: "Mi presión arterial se disparó, perdí el control de todo mi cuerpo, me desmayé en un rincón, me desperté en una hamaca 6 horas más tarde, y me sentí como Dios durante 2 días". (Risas) Un químico italiano leyó esto y dijo: "No me interesan para nada los aspectos teológicos de la rana mono verde. ¿Pero qué es esto de la variación de la presión arterial?" Hablamos de un químico italiano que está trabajando en un nuevo tratamiento para la hipertensión basado en los péptidos de la piel de la rana mono verde, y de otros científicos que están buscando una cura para el estafilococo dorado, resistente a los medicamentos. Qué ironía si estos indígenas aislados con su rana mágica resultan ser una de las curas. Este es un chamán ayahuasca del noroeste del Amazonas, en medio de la ceremonia de yagé. Lo llevé a Los Ángeles para reunirse con un empleado de una fundación en busca de fondos para proteger su cultura. El hombre miró al curandero y le dijo: "Ud. no estudió medicina, ¿verdad?" El chamán respondió: "No". "Bueno, entonces, ¿qué puede saber acerca de sanidad?" El chamán le miró y dijo: "Ud. sabe que si tiene una infección, hay que ir al médico, pero muchas enfermedades humanas son males del corazón, la mente y el espíritu. La medicina occidental no puede curarlos. Yo los trato". (Aplausos) Pero no todo es color de rosa a la hora de aprender sobre nuevos medicamentos a partir de la naturaleza. Esta es una víbora de Brasil, cuyo veneno se estudió en la Universidade de São Paulo. Más tarde, se fabricaron inhibidores ECA, un tratamiento de vanguardia para la hipertensión. La hipertensión es la causa de más del 10 % de todas las muertes diarias en el mundo. Se trata de una industria de USD 4000 millones basada en el veneno de una víbora brasileña, y los brasileños no recibieron un centavo. Esta no es una manera aceptable de hacer negocios. A la selva tropical se la llama: "máxima expresión de la vida terrestre". Hay un dicho en Surinam que me gusta mucho: "Las selvas tropicales aguardan respuestas a las preguntas que todavía tenemos que hacer". Pero como todos Uds. saben, está desapareciendo rápidamente. Aquí en Brasil, en el Amazonas, en todo el mundo. Tomé esta foto de un pequeño avión al sobrevolar la frontera oriental de la reserva indígena xingú, en el estado de Mato Grosso al noroeste de aquí. En la mitad superior de la imagen, se ve dónde viven los indígenas. La línea del medio es la frontera oriental de la reserva. En la mitad superior están los indígenas, en la mitad inferior están los blancos. Arriba, los medicamentos milagrosos, abajo, solo un montón de vacas flacas. Arriba, el carbono queda capturado en el bosque, donde pertenece, abajo, el carbono es liberado en la atmósfera donde provoca el cambio climático. De hecho, la segunda causa por la cual el carbono se libera en la atmósfera es la destrucción del bosque. Pero cuando hablamos de la destrucción es importante tener en cuenta que el Amazonas es el paisaje más poderoso de todos. Es un lugar lleno de belleza y maravillas. El oso hormiguero más grande del mundo vive en la selva tropical, y puede pesar hasta 40 kg. La tarántula Goliat o araña come pájaros es la araña más grande del mundo. Se encuentra en el Amazonas también. La envergadura de las alas del águila arpía tiene más de 2 metros. Y el caimán negro... este monstruo puede llegar a pesar más de media tonelada. Son conocidos por ser devoradores de hombres. La anaconda, la serpiente más grande, el capibara, el roedor más grande. Una ejemplar de aquí, de Brasil, llegó a 91 kg. Veamos dónde viven estas criaturas, visitemos el noreste del Amazonas, el hogar de la tribu akuriyo. Los pueblos aislados juegan un papel místico e icónico en nuestra imaginación. Son los que mejor conocen la naturaleza. Son los que realmente viven en total armonía con la naturaleza. Según nuestros estándares, a algunos se les calificaría como pueblos primitivos. "No conocían el fuego, por lo menos cuando se les contactó por primera vez". Pero conocen el bosque mucho mejor que nosotros. Las akuriyos tienen 35 palabras para la miel, y otros indígenas los catalogan como los verdaderos maestros de la tierra-esmeralda. Esta es la cara de mi amigo, Pohnay. Cuando yo era adolescente y escuchaba a los Rolling Stones en Nueva Orleans, Pohnay era un nómada del bosque, vagando por el noreste de la selva amazónica con un pequeño grupo, en busca de venado, plantas medicinales y de una esposa entre los otros pequeños grupos nómadas. Pero es la gente como él, que sabe cosas que nosotros no sabemos, y tienen mucho que enseñarnos. Pero si uno entra en la mayoría de los bosques del Amazonas, no hay pueblos indígenas. Esto es lo que encontrarán: tallas en rocas que estos pueblos indígenas, estos pueblos no contactados, han dejado al afilar sus hachas. Estas culturas que antaño bailaron, hicieron el amor, cantaron a sus dioses, y adoraron al bosque, todo lo que queda de ellos es una marca en la piedra, como la que Uds. ven aquí. Vamos al oeste de la Amazonia, que es el epicentro de los pueblos aislados. Cada uno de estos puntos representa un pequeño pueblo indígena aislado, y hoy, la gran noticia es que creemos que hay 14 o 15 grupos aislados solo en la Amazonia colombiana. ¿Por qué esta gente está aislada? Saben que existimos, que hay un mundo exterior. Es una forma de resistencia. Han optado por permanecer aislados, y creo que es su derecho seguir estándolo. ¿Por qué se esconden estas tribus de los hombres? He aquí por qué. Obviamente, esto empezó en 1492. Pero a finales del siglo pasado el detonante fue el comercio del caucho. La demanda de caucho natural, que venía de la Amazonia, fue el equivalente botánico a la fiebre del oro. Caucho para neumáticos de bicicleta, para neumáticos de automóviles, goma para zepelines. La loca carrera por conseguir el caucho fue la razón, y el hombre de la izquierda, Julio Arana, uno de los verdaderos villanos de la historia. Su gente, su empresa, y otras compañías como la suya mataron, masacraron, torturaron y exterminaron a los indígenas como Witoto que ven a la derecha de la foto. Aún hoy, cuando salen de la selva, rara vez la historia tiene un final feliz. Estos son nukaks. Fueron contactados en los años 80. Un año después, los mayores de 40 habían muerto. Y recuerden, son sociedades ágrafas. Los ancianos son las bibliotecas. Cada vez que muere un chamán, es como si una biblioteca se hubiera incendiado. Se han visto obligados a abandonar sus tierras. Los narcotraficantes se han apoderado de las tierras nukak, y los nukaks viven como mendigos en parques públicos al este de Colombia. Desde las tierras nukak, los quiero llevar al suroeste, a uno de los paisajes más espectaculares del mundo: el Parque Nacional Chiribiquete. Alrededor de él, vivían 3 tribus aisladas y gracias al gobierno colombiano y a los colegas colombianos, sigue creciendo. Es más grande que el estado de Maryland. Es un tesoro importante de diversidad botánica. Fue explorado botánicamente por primera vez en 1943 por mi mentor, Richard Schultes, lo pueden ver aquí en la cima de la montaña Bell, la montaña sagrada de los karijonas. Les mostraré cómo se ve ahora. Al sobrevolar Chiribiquete, podemos ver que las montañas aún están perdidas, ningún científico ha subido a la cima. De hecho, nadie ha vuelto a subir a la cima de la montaña Bell desde Schultes en el año 1943. Les llevaré hasta aquí en la montaña Bell justo al este de la imagen. Les enseñaré cómo se ve hoy en día. Esto no es solo un tesoro de diversidad botánica, no solo es el hogar de 3 tribus aisladas, también es el mayor tesoro de arte precolombino en el mundo: más de 200 000 pinturas. El científico holandés Thomas van der Hammen la describió como la Capilla Sixtina de la selva amazónica. Pero pasemos de Chiribiquete al sureste, de nuevo en la Amazonia colombiana. Recuerden, la Amazonia colombiana es más grande que Nueva Inglaterra. La selva amazónica es enorme, y Brasil tiene una gran parte, pero no toda ella. Vamos a dos parques nacionales, Cahuinari y Puré, en la Amazonia colombiana —-esta es la frontera con Brasil a la derecha—- hogar de varios grupos de pueblos aislados y no contactados. Los conocedores pueden observar los techos de estas malocas, estas casas comunales, y ver que hay diversidad cultural. Estas son, de hecho, tribus diferentes. Así aisladas como están, les mostraré cómo el mundo exterior les está invadiendo: Aquí vemos un aumento del comercio y del transporte en el Putumayo. Al apaciguarse la guerra civil en Colombia, el mundo exterior empieza a notarse. Al norte, tenemos explotaciones ilegales de oro, también al este, en Brasil. Se ha incrementado la caza y la pesca con fines comerciales. Vemos talas ilegal de madera al sur y narcotraficantes que tratan de usar el parque para entrar en Brasil. Y esta es la razón por la cual, en el pasado, no había que meterse con los indígenas aislados. Y si parece que la foto es borrosa es porque fue tomada de prisa, y el motivo (Risas) Esto parece... (Aplausos) Esto parece un hangar de la Amazonia brasileña, pero se trata de una exposición de arte en La Habana, Cuba por parte de un grupo llamado Los Carpinteros. Esta es su percepción del porqué no debemos meternos con los indígenas. Pero el mundo está cambiando. Estos son los mashco-piros en la frontera entre Brasil y Perú que han huido de la selva porque fueron esencialmente expulsados por los narcotraficantes y leñadores. Y en Perú, hay un negocio de muy dudosa legalidad; los llamamos safaris humanos. Se visita grupos aislados para tomarles una foto. Por supuesto, cuando uno les da ropa y herramientas, también le regala enfermedades. Los llamamos "safaris inhumanos". Estos son indígenas en la frontera de Perú que fueron sobrevolados por los misioneros que quieren ir para convertirlos al cristianismo. Sabemos cómo acaba esto. ¿Qué hacer? Introducir tecnología en las tribus contactadas, no en los pueblos indígenas aislados, de manera respetuosa con su cultura. Este es el matrimonio perfecto de la antigua sabiduría chamánica y la tecnología del siglo XXI. Lo hemos hecho hasta ahora con más de 30 tribus, hemos cartografiado, gestionado y ofrecido una mayor protección a más de 70 millones de hectáreas de selva tropical ancestral. (Aplausos) Esto permite a los indígenas controlar su entorno y su destino cultural. También se establecieron casetas de vigilancia para alejar a los extraños. Estos son indígenas, entrenados como guardaparques indígenas, que patrullan las fronteras y mantienen al resto del mundo a distancia. Esta es una foto de un contacto real. Estos son indígenas chitonahua en la frontera entre Brasil y Perú. Salieron de la selva en busca de ayuda. Les dispararon, y sus malocas, sus casas comunales fueron quemadas. Algunos de ellos fueron masacrados. El uso de armas automáticas para masacrar a la gente no contactada es uno de los abusos más viles y repugnantes en contra de los derechos humanos que hay en nuestro planeta en este momento y tiene que parar. (Aplausos) Pero permítanme concluir diciendo que este trabajo puede ser gratificante desde un punto de vista espiritual, pero es difícil y puede ser peligroso. Dos colegas míos fallecieron recientemente al estrellarse con una avioneta. Ayudaban en el bosque protegiendo a esos pueblos indígenas no contactados. Así que, en conclusión, la pregunta es: ¿cómo será el futuro? Este es el pueblo uray en Brasil. ¿Qué depara el futuro para ellos, y que depara el futuro para nosotros? Pensemos de manera diferente. Hagamos un mundo mejor. Si el clima va a cambiar, vamos a hacer de ello algo para mejor y no para peor. Vivamos en un planeta lleno de vegetación exuberante, donde los pueblos aislados puedan permanecer no contactados, manteniendo ese misterio y ese conocimiento si así lo deciden. Vivimos en un mundo donde los chamanes puedan vivir en estos bosques para sanarse a sí mismos y a nosotros con sus plantas místicas y sus ranas sagradas. Gracias de nuevo. (Aplausos)